[Music]
good morning good morning do you know
how to find the center of gravity of any
object here it's somewhere in the middle
what you do is you put it on your
hands and then just push the hands
together towards each other and I don't
have to look what I'm doing you see
that that's where the center of gravity
is it's interesting huh so first one of
the hands starts sliding so this comes
too close to the center but then it
stops on the other hand
St I'm not purposefully doing this all
I'm doing
is and putting pressure from both sides
and just keep keep
going and
automatically the
object Finds Its Own center of
gravity
nice something you can take home each
day yesterday we introduced the idea of
transversal intersection you see things
can be intersecting like this that's
transversal like this that's not
transversal like this that's
transversal but like this that's not
transversal and we saw that if you have
a transversal
intersection you can Jiggle It you can
part up it and it's still transversal
and if you have a non transversal
intersection small paration will make it
transversal okay so transversal St
ations are generic non transversal ones
and exceptional as we have met time and
again that's the beginning of
topological thinking so today we'll
Begin by learning how to count the
number of transversal intersections we
have already done this we said how many
times this and this intersect with plus
or minus signs do you remember some
sometimes the intersection is plus
sometimes minus but in order to count
plus or minus with sign we have to have
the
orientations so with respect to sum
orientation you get plus sum orientation
you get minus so definition is as
follows let's suppose that we have an
oriented manifold that is a manifold on
which an orientation is chosen we'll see
plenty of examples so don't worry too
much about the actual definition let K
and L be um or oriented sub
manifes two geometric FES intersecting
inside some ambient
space
now let's first consider the case when
those two sub
manifes are like this do you remember
how to read that
single Nadia do you remember
this
this strange symbol which apparently is
not
aaric um you remember this means that
they intersect
transversally in
m a symbol that we introduced last time
which you have to remember today because
we'll be using it from now on they
intersect
transversally okay if they are
intersecting transversely which happens
most
often the intersection number
of K and L in this order so we have to
say intersection number K and L and if
you say the intersection number of L and
K the result might be different K and L
in this
order is we write it like this
K little circle
L not K do l no no no not K cross l no
no no not K Smiley l no no no K little
circle L this is simply equal to the sum
over all the um intersection
points
of the sign of the
intersection at
P I hope this makes sense we have done
many examples of this kind and we'll do
more where the the
sign is plus or minus accordingly as so
all of these numbers are plus or minus
and you're adding plus plus sorry plus -
one plus - one and so on accordingly as
the joint
orientation of K and L again in this
[Applause]
order match is or
not or the same or the
opposite the orientation of M the
ambient orientation of
M
that's the ACT
this definition when K and L
are do you remember what this means what
does it
mean they
intersect transversally please practice
saying this word a few times
transversally
okay they intersect transversally
excellent so people now remember what
this means now suppose that in contrast
they don't intersect transversally in
M yeah what do we do well the thing that
we always do in mathematics let's first
deform this
station K and
L into
transversality funny expression but you
I hope you understand what it means so
you shake them and then you make the
intersection of transversal and then you
apply the definition okay so that's um
and then
count count the intersection
number there is a problem with this
logical problem this which is that maybe
if you perturb in different ways into
transparity you get the different count
depending on how you p in fact it does
not and the fact
that
this um number does not depend on the
way you
PB the intersection number is
independent independ
independent of how we
deform
will be proved later
on in cor I'm going to write it later on
dater
okay a
question there is a mistake on this
Blackboard please find it what is
it independ
D not not
dend in English Okay good people are
still
awake let's see if we all stay awake
until the
end okay now although it's we never
reuse this
generalization in any major
way there is a slight generalization of
the concept of intersection number when
when various objects are not oriented
indeed it's useful to be able to count
the intersection number in nonorientable
stations do you remember any example of
non-orientable objects yes movie strip
can I anything
else there was a whole family of
non-orientable things you
remember so n ngg so all those things
that we call NS those are the connected
sums of real projected plans but anyway
there are nonorientable stations in real
life they arise quite often in
applications and it would be nice to do
the intersection Theory
but it's
um awkward we cannot say plus or minus 1
2 3 4 and so on so in
uh I have to erase this
in nonorientable
cations for example on n g that's
correct
um we can do the
theory mode two what do we mean by mode
two means that one it's a strange
arithmetic 1 + 0 is 1 0 + 0 is 0 and 0 +
1 is 1 but 1 + 1 is 0 so + 1 = -1 so we
don't have to worry whether something is
plus or minus all we know is that
something exists or does not exist and
if it exists twice then it's zero that's
mode two and if you do this we don't
have to worry about orientation as you
can imagine this is less than the
integer intersection Theory but
sometimes it's useful okay let's see an
example so that we understand what this
number is please draw an enormously
large to us because we need all that
space and the first curve that we shall
draw is this
curve that's the cve that we should call
K do you
see as I see where this curve is I
imagine this
Taurus like that and this curve is at
the top of the
Taurus H do you see this okay by the way
if you're drawing that kind of picture
you should not draw it like this because
this curve does not look like it's on
the top of the
Taurus this curve looks like it's on the
top of the
Taurus you see the difference
that's how you Le to draw
okay the next curve is rather more
complicated we shall imagine a curve
that comes
in and then starts going around this
storus and goes
around and then arrives here and then
keeps going
I'll explain what this is and then goes
in the
back and then comes out in
front and we shall call this L and it
will be going in this direction and here
it will go up in this
direction do you see see what this does
imagine a
Taurus and this curve is on the outside
of Taurus but at this point when it
comes in front of you it bends and goes
around this Taurus once and twice and
then he keeps going on the outside of
to and then comes back again once
twice I hope you can picture
this okay yes any question and we are
going to
introduce an orientation on the Taurus
which will be the one that you
expect E1 and E2 in this order as seen
from the
outside all right now a question the
yellow curve K and the pink curve L
intersect in how many
points twice
this is one intersection this is another
intersection that's
correct what is the sign of this
intersection on the
left any take
[Music]
us Sarah do you have an
idea positive why because k at this
point is going this way yeah L is going
this way yeah it looks like it's going
this way but it's actually going this
way because it's at top of the Taurus
yeah K and L that joint orientation is
that the same or opposite as E1 and E2
it is the same as you can see so this is
positive how about the one on the right
s positive it's also
positive you agree okay so these are are
two positives and the intersection
number then of these two things is + one
+ one and it's +
two
good I hope this is
clear next I should go to that
Blackboard because we are dra drawing
something interesting but again large
scale we shall
draw two curves two loops
inside the um two dimensional plane so
R2 you can try to draw anything you like
it doesn't matter what you draw but
please make it complicated
enough wow can you distinguish them
maybe I should use different colors let
me use different
colors
the advantage of color vision now when I
use colors I'm going to draw something
different okay I'm going to trace
because I canot I canot draw it again
okay I'm going to trace these things
that's
yellow I hope you understand what I have
just drawn I'm not drawing anything in
particular I'm drawing something
random yes okay and this is the pink
curve
yep yep okay let's say that the pink
curve is going this way so it's going
this way it's going this way it's going
that way it's going this way and the
yellow curve which way shall we go let's
say this is K let's go this way shall we
and then it's going this way it's going
this way here it's going that way it
comes down this way and then joins up
clear and as usual we shall take the
ambient orientation but just because we
want to exercise let's take this
orientation in
R2 the plane of the Blackboard is R2 and
we take this orientation please notice
it is the orientation opposite to the
usual
orientation okay now there are people
who are feeling sleepy because all all
this is easy but that's
count how many intersections are there
Lots here please count because I'm going
to lose I and also I cannot count Beyond
three 1 two three many many
many many many many many many many many
many many intersections how
many
14 what 14 15 which one is it I I'm
afraid that there are people in this
room who cannot come okay let's figure
out what these signs
are
okay how about
this let's ask Hamid for
example Hamid good morning um no no I
know that you're working very hard so
I'm sorry to interrupt but this
intersection is it positive or negative
if the ambient orientation is like
this so I'm talking about k l in this
order so K here is going this way yeah
and L is is going this way K and L is
that positive or negative with respect
to
this negative yeah indeed I think it's
negative because k l in this order when
I turn around and just it's going to be
k l in this order which does not match
the ambient orientation so that's
negative how about
here huh somebody said
say
that hey I can't hear how about
can negative it's negative so K goes
this way L goes this way k
l yeah is it negative
k l k l and that's one two so which one
is it positive yes that's positive how
about this one
K and L this
way that's negative what do you think
now without thinking what do you think
this
is I think it's positive too I think I
have detected the same pattern that all
of you are detecting and let's check
that it is positive here K is going this
way here K is going this way no it's
going this way thank you very much and L
is going this way K and L if you look at
this one two it is positive ah so I
think this is negative no this is
positive this is probably negative this
is
positive but if this is positive this
had better be negative
right but it is so one
minus now what is
this it should be positive and let's
check that it is positive because it's
been a long time so k and l k l it's
positive it's positive but now that's
positive that's
negative this must be positive was it
positive yes it was positive okay so I
think we understand what's going
on so what is this it is equal to - 1 +
1 - 1 + 1 -1 + 1 -1 + 1 - 1 + 1 - 1 + 1
- 1 +
1 H which
equals zero interesting
question can we
draw in R2 with any
orientation two
Loops intersecting
loops
whose intersection
number is not
zero question
well is shaking her
head and inde in this example
there is a pattern which seems to result
in automatic zero but we don't know that
it's always the
case there's
some evidence because in this case these
will have different signs opposite
signs in this case these will have
opposite signs and so on so
experimentation
suggests what do you think it suggests
no
no but we don't we are not completely
sure and if you want to be sure please
wait until cor
okay
yes yeah
that you see but we are talking yes
that's right so you can have something
like this and something like
this yeah now that's an interesting
question because this is still going to
give you
zero suppose that we have something like
this that's still going to give you zero
what if we have
something like this you think it's going
to give you zero maybe it's going to
give you zero and so on there are many
different possibilities so I'd like to
leave it um as a research idea for you
and we shall give the answer in a moment
but for the time being make you you know
whenever you see a problem like this
it's natural to ask the teacher well are
we are we allowed to have self
intersections but let's think of it this
way you have now found an interesting
possibility make the problem as
interesting as possible for you to
solve yeah so even if the te teacher
says no you're not allowed to have
intersections well try to have
intersections and see what
happens so maybe it leads to something
new or maybe doesn't lead to something
new either way you'll have discovered
something on your
own okay so that's how you can start
doing mathematics often we just listen
to what the teacher tells you and then
you do exactly what the teacher says but
you and I'm very happy have found an
interesting window of possibility your
own possibility so you should
investigate it on your even if I say yes
no ignore what Tashi says you are doing
mathematics on your own okay that was a
lot
of detailed explanation so let's go on
to um a few more bits of general
theory we said earlier that the order in
which we count the intersection number k
L was important let's see what happens
if we take the sub force in the opposite
to that L little Circle K how is that
related to k l well it's obvious to all
of us that it's going to get plus or
minus sign but it doesn't always become
minus it turns out instead we have a
sign which is 1 - 1 to the^ small K *
small L where where as you can imagine
small K is the dimension of capital K
and the small L is the dimension of
capital L please note that this is minus
one to^ k * L not k+
L
okay this is what happens and you should
be able to do experimentation on
yourself and here is how it works in
general let's say that you
have some sort of L
okay and then some sort of
K this is a very abstract picture so you
have to exercise your imagination they
intersec in this point this can be for
example a onedimensional
curve this can be a two- dimensional
surface so it can be piercing the
surface somewhere for example but it can
be five dimensional object six
dimensional object in an 11 dimensional
space that's fine too okay how do we
count the intersection well here
officially we look at the frame of
reference or basis of tangent vectors to
K in other words we look at the tangent
space to
K flat thing which touches K in this
direction and we ask what are the
tangent vectors and I have lost the
yellow choke thank you very much it's
over
here and black the red chalk let's say
that we have a number of vectors E1
E2 and so
on up to e they are K vectors here
tangent in this direction in the case k
was one dimensional there was only one
vector which was this
Arrow yeah but in general they are K
vectors similarly we are going to take
the tangent plane to l
and then we should consider vectors
fub1 FS2 these are all independent up to
how many of them are there f l so F okay
so that's the situation that we have
Okay so let's say that
E1 e and fub1 through f l define The
Joint
orientation
look at the
definition at the point of intersection
okay of K and
L and L in this
order okay and the question is whether
this joint orientation matches or
mismatches the ambient orientation of
M matches plus one mismatches minus one
okay The Joint Ori
orentation now
of L and
K in the opposite order
yeah the opposite
order is defined
by
I think I'm going to write it so F1
through f l E1 through E Yeah in that um
order